Guide to the [Political cartoons concerning France, 1789-1914 (bulk 1789-1815)]
Political cartoons concerning France, 1789-1914 (bulk 1789-1815)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
[Political cartoons concerning France, 1789-1914 (bulk 1789-1815)]
8552
76 prints:
Political cartoons and caricatures.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
French Revolution period caricatures mainly concerning the three estates of France, the nationalization of church property, privileges of the clergy and nobility, despotism, the constitution of 1791, and the political process.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
French Revolution period caricatures mainly concerning the three estates of France, the nationalization of church property, privileges of the clergy and nobility, despotism, the constitution of 1791, and the political process. Included are Adieu Bastille, Le Dentiste National, and La Nation Française Assistée de M. de la Fayette. Includes one German caricature by P. Scherz, engraved by Brunee. Napoleonic period caricatures consist mainly of hand-colored engravings and etchings, many of them French or German caricatures of Napoleon which satirize his military setbacks or note the carnage caused by his military campaigns. These include Triumph des Jahres 1813; Ach! Papa, Welche schöne Seifenblasen hast du gemacht; Georges édenté; Der Rheinische Courier; and others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Charles King of France, 1757-1836; George King of Great Britain, 1738-1820; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834; Louis King of France, 1754-1793; Louis King of France, 1755-1824; Louis Philippe, King of the French, 1773-1850; Metternich, Clemens Wenzel Lothar, Fürst von, 1773-1859; Maury, Jean Siffrein, 1746-1817; Mirabeau, vicomte de, 1754-1795; Montesquiou-Fezensac, François-Xavier-Marc-Antoine, duc de, 1757-1832; Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, 1754-1838; Wellington, Arthur Wellesley, Duke of, 1769-1852; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834; Grandville, J. J., 1803-1847.; Isabey, Jean-Baptiste, 1767-1855.; Philipon, Charles, 1800-1862.; Bastille.; Bastille; Congress of Vienna; Revolution (France: 1789-1799)
Subjects:
Political culture -- France.; Press and politics -- France.; Clergy -- France.; Estates (Social orders) -- France.; Nobility -- France.; Privileges and immunities -- France.; Despotism -- France.; Censorship -- History -- 19th century. -- France; Leipzig, Battle of, Leipzig, Germany, 1813.; Thermidor (French Revolution); Clergy; Despotism; Estates (Social orders); Nobility; Political culture; Political science; Press and politics; Privileges and immunities; Public opinion, British; Public opinion, German
Places:
France -- History -- July Revolution, 1830; France -- Art and the revolution. -- Revolution, 1789-1799; France -- Politics and government -- 1789-1799.; France -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; France -- Foreign public opinion. -- Revolution, 1789-1799; France -- Constitution.; France
Form and Genre Terms:
Engravings -- Colored -- 1789-1799. -- France; Etchings -- Colored -- 1789-1799. -- France; Caricatures -- 18th century. -- France; Caricatures -- 19th century. -- France; Caricatures -- 19th century. -- Germany; Engravings -- Colored -- 18th century. -- France; Engravings -- Colored -- 19th century. -- France; Engravings -- Colored -- 19th century. -- Germany; Art; Constitution; History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Title devised by cataloger.
Related materials are held at Cornell in the Lafayette Collection; the Graphics, Pamphlets, Newspapers, and Books components of the French Revolution Collection; and the general Rare Books collection. All are located in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections.
Former call numbers: Archives DC140.9 .F87 Box 1-5+++ (under title French Revolution political caricatures); Archives DC140.9 .F87 Box 7-12+++ (under title Nineteenth-century political caricatures concerning France). Items housed in Archives DC140.9 .F87 Box 7-12+++ included an album of anti-Napoleon caricatures with previous call number Rare DC203.4C27++.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Attacks against the Old Rgime and Legal Privileges (before July 1789)
Series II. Storming of the Bastille (14 July 1789)
Series III. Abolition of Aristocracy and Nationalization of Church Property (August-November 1789)
Series IV. Celebration of National Unity, Fte de la Federation (14 July 1790), Constitutional Monarchy
Series V. Satire against Royalists, Emigrs, and the Conservative Church
Series VI. Outside Perception of the French Revolution
Series VII. Revolutionary War in Europe (1791-1798)
Series VIII. Comité de Salut Public and “Reign of Terror”
Series IX. Fall of Robespierre, Thermidorian Reaction
Series X. Reign of Napoleon I. Official Propaganda Celebrating His Victories as well as the New Dynasty
Series X. Hostile Caricatures and French-Bashing (1813-1815)
Series XI. The First Bourbon Restauration (April 1814-March 1815) and the Cent-Jours (March-July 1815)
Series XII. Second Restauration (1815-1830)
CONTAINER LIST
- Attacks against the Old Rgime and Legal Privileges (before July 1789), 1789
  - “A Faut esperer queu se jeu…”, 1789; 1; 26.2 x 21.7 cm; Print shows the nobility and the clergy riding on the back of a man representing the third estate or working class; the man is bent under their weight and supports, while around his feet birds and rabbits (which he cannot hunt) feast on the produce of his labor. (Box 1, Item 1)
    Described as follows in the Catalogue of the Library of A.D. White (Cornell, 1894): “Colored engraving showing a bishop and a nobleman astride of an old peasant, who moves slowly, supported by his mattock, while pigeons and hares devour his grain and vegetables about his feet... For a sequel of this caricature, see J’savois ben, etc.” (p. 293)
    France
  - “La France Figurée sous un Globe est soutenu du Peuple. La Noblesse et le Clergé”, 1789; 2; 27.2 x 20 cm (Box 1)
- Storming of the Bastille (14 July 1789), 1789
  - “Réveil du Tiers-Etat: “Ma feinte, il doit tems que je me réveillisse [sic]…”, 1789; 3; 20.6 x 25.3 cm (Box 1)
  - “Adieu Bastille”, 1789; 4; 20.5 x 29.8 cm (Box 1)
    Available on Shared Shelf Commons: RMC2007_0369
- Abolition of Aristocracy and Nationalization of Church Property (August-November 1789), 1789-1790
  - "J’savois ben qu’j’aurions not’ tour", 1789; 5; 28 x 20.3 cm (Box 1)
  - “Ha je seront bien content quand j’aurons tous ces papiers la”, 1789; 6; 29 x 19.5 cm (Box 1)
  - “Ils les avaients [sic] trop longs”, 1789; 7; 28 x 23 cm (Box 1)
  - “Les Trois ordres… sous le niveau”, 1789; 8; 10.5 x 7. 5 cm (Box 1)
  - "L'Abb d'autre fois. L'Abb d'aujourd'hui", 1790; 9; 11. 5 x 8 cm (Box 1)
  - "Grand mal de cœur de Monseigneur: Courage Mrg vous allé́ vous purgée [sic] de chose bien utile pour votre salut", 1790; 10; 19 x 24.5 cm (Box 1)
  - "Le Dentiste National", 1789; 11; 18 x 26 cm (Box 1)
  - "Trois têtes sous le même bonnet”, 1789; 12; 20 x 30.3 cm (Box 1)
  - “Ma finte, Monsieur, je crois que vot’ habit d’officier m’ira ben !”, 1789; 13; 27.5 x 20 cm (Box 1)
  - “Un seul fait les trois”, 1789; 14; 22.5 x 28.5 cm (Box 1)
- Celebration of National Unity, Fte de la Federation (14 July 1790), Constitutional Monarchy, 1789-1791
  - “Bon nous voilà d’accord”, 1789; 15; 14. 5 x 14 cm (Box 2)
    Available on Shared Shelf Common: RMC2009_0125
  - "Par moi vous tes tous frres", 1789; 16; 24 x 20 cm (Box 2)
  - "Tôt tôt tôt battez chaud tôt tôt tôt bon courrage il faut avoir cœur à l'ouvrage", 1789; 17; 18.5 x 18 cm (Box 2)
    Available on Shared Shelf Common; RMC2007_0367
  - No Title, showing the three estates as part of the same carriage, 1789; 18; 26 x 21.5 cm (Box 2)
  - “Magicienne Consultée sur la Révolution de 1789: orgueil dompté, avarice punie, mérite reconnû [sic], union des quatre parties du monde”, 1789; 19; 24 x 32 cm (Box 2)
  - "La Nation française assistée de Mr de la Fayette terrasse le despotisme et les abus du règne féodal…", 1789; 20; 27 x 18.5 cm (Box 2)
  - “Ha, je seront bien content quand j’aurons tous ces papiers-là: Le trésor tiré des ténèbres”, 1790-1791; 21; 29 x 19.5 cm (Box 2)
- Satire against Royalists, Emigrs, and the Conservative Church, 1789-1792
  - “Le Pied de Nez ou l’Aristocratie écrasée”, 1789; 22; 23 x 27 cm (Box 2)
  - Un Monstre a trois têtes désignant les trois Etats de l'aristocratie s'occupe à dévorer le reste du cadavre du peuple qu'il à englouti impitoyablement dans ses entrailles carnivores: il est précédé du fanatisme aux queus [sic] de dragon et qui est vêtu d'un froc monacal, il porte à califourchon sur son dos l'hypocrisie pressante, un serpent qui distille son poison aristocratique, 1789; 71; 20. 5 x 35 cm (Box 2)
  - [High Clergy, Parliaments, and Nobility, in the Persons of Maury, d’Eprémesnil and Mirabeau-Tonneau] « On ne peut trop les punir, ils nous ont fait assez souffrir: Labor omnia vincit improbus », 1789; 23; 25 x 38 cm (Box 2)
  - "Monsieur Veto: quel est donc ce Mr Veto, qui seul fait plus de bruit que n'en fit Figaro sans doute il n'est pas né dans le canton de Berne. Veut du peuple faire un zéro, etc", 1790; 24; 14 x 20.5 cm (Box 2)
  - "Curé de St ....... accompagné de deux diables descend dans l'empire des démons pour demander a Belzebuth leurs princes des secours pour tacher s'il est possible d'empêcher l'exécution de la Constitution civile ecclésiastique. Ou va-t'en au diable", 1791; 25; 25 x 20 cm (Box 2)
  - “Le Tiers-Etat mariant les religieux avec les religieuses: en faisant une si bonne action, nous garantissons des cornes”, 1790; 26; 17.5 x 27.5 cm (Box 2)
  - “Saint Pierre Reniant le Pape Pie VI”, 1791; 27; 23.5 x 17 cm (Box 2)
  - “M. le marquis de Vieille Roche protestant contre les Decrets de l'Assemblée Nationale; M. le vieux Marechal Aristocrate effraié de la bourasque parisienne; L'Officier Aristocrate mettant les pouces devant les patriotes français; M. le Chevalier, ancien Courtisan sans titres ni pension”, 1791-1792; 28 (Box 2)
  - "Retour de Deux Emigrans", 1791-1792; 29; 23 x 30.5 cm (Box 2)
- Outside Perception of the French Revolution, 1792
  - "D Frankreichs Lillie!", 1792; 72; 22.5x37 cm (Box 2)
    Contains optical illusion images of 14 heads of state and political revolutionaries including Robespierre, Hebert, and Orleans
    Germany
- Revolutionary War in Europe (1791-1798), 1791-1798
  - "Subsistances portées par le duc Dyork à Toulon: on voit ce qu'il y avait dans le sac; le grain seul reste sur le terrein de la liberté́, qu'il abandonne, ayant le nez cassé et le sceptre ses espérances étant rompu", 1794; 30; 36 x 26 cm (Box 2)
  - "Départ de l'Anglais du continent: chargé de son moulin sans grain, portant sa gentille meunière, ce triste Anglais s'en va bon train, qu'and Jacquot lui souffle au derrière", undated; 31; 28.5 x 19.5 cm (Box 2)
  - "Die grosse und merkwurdige Regierungsrevolution der Bataver Republick… am 12 Juni 1798", 1798; 32; 20 x 26 cm (Box 2)
    As a general in the French revolutionary army of General Charles Pichegru and commander of the Batavian Legion. Daendels helped Dutch politician Pieter Vreede to power in a coup d'tat on 25 January 1798. The reign of Vreede did not bring the expected results, however, and Daendels supported another coup d'tat against Vreede on 14 June 1798]
  - An Emblematical View of the Constitutions of England and France, 1791; 73; 10.5x13.5 (Box 2)
    England
- Comité de Salut Public and “Reign of Terror”, 1793-1794
  - "Vive la LibertVive la Libert", 1793; 33; 17. 2 x 14.4 cm (Box 2)
    Described as follows in the Catalogue of the Historical Library of A.D. White (1894): “Colored engraving representing a prisoner in a dimly lighted cell, standing on a bunch of straw, chained by waist and neck to the wall, and uttering the above exclamation” (p. 296)
  - “Guillotine”, 1794; 34; 12 x 15 cm (Box 2)
    England (?)
- Fall of Robespierre, Thermidorian Reaction, 1795-1799
  - "Signalement Des Chouans et Autres Contrevolutionaires [sic]: Officiers gnraux de l'arme thermidorienne sortant du Caff de Chartres allant en expditions arms de btons", 1795-1799; 35; 28.5 x 19.55 cm (Box 3)
  - "Ėmigrand [sic] revenant a Paris", 1795-1799; 36; 24.5 x 1.5 cm (Box 3)
  - “Le Petit Coblentz”, 1795-1799; 37; Isabey, Jean-Baptiste; 19 x 15 cm (Box 3)
    Available on Shared Shelf Commons: RMC2007_0368
- Reign of Napoleon I. Official Propaganda Celebrating His Victories as well as the New Dynasty, 1806-1813
  - Official Propaganda Celebrating His Victories as well as the New Dynasty
    - Entrevue de Napolon le Grand, 1.er Empereur des Franais et Roi d'Italie, avec Franois II. Empereur d'Allemagne [after Austerlitz, 1805], 1806; 38; 22.2 x 34.1 cm (Box 3)
    - Combat de Saalfeld et Mort du Prince Louis de Prusse, 1806; 39; 22.2 x 34.1 cm (Box 3)
    - "Georges [King George III. of England], dent. Quand il n'aura pas plus de dents il ne mordra plus!", 1806; 40; 20.4 x 27 cm (Box 3)
    - "Trait de prudence du Lord Morpeth: Envoy d'Angleterre auprs du Cabinet Prussien il ne se trouvait qu'a 6 lieues du champ de bataille pendant la journe d'Jena il entend le canon ... court ... offre 60 guines pour un cheval l'obtient et se sauve", 1806; 41; 16.5 x 15.1 cm (Box 3)
    - “Famille Impériale et Royale de Napoléon le Grand premier du nom, Empereur des Français, Roi d'Italie, et Protecteur de la Confédération du Rhin", 1810; 42; 23 x 36 cm (Box 3)
    - “Promenade du Petit Roi de Rome au bord de l’eau”, 1813; 43; 30 x 24 cm (Box 3)
- Hostile Caricatures and French-Bashing (1813-1815), 1812-1815
  - “Triumph des Jahres 1813”, 1813; 44; Henschel, Gebrder; 12 x 9.3 cm (Box 3)
  - “Die neue Europaeische Barbierstube”, 1813; 45; Voltz, Johann Michael; 16 x 14 cm (Box 3)
  - “A la Cosaka”, 1812-1813; 46; 16 x 12 cm (Box 3)
    Available on Shared Shelf Commons: RMC2008_1144
    Germany (?)
  - "Der neue Universalmonarch", 1814; 47; Voltz, Johann Michael; 16 x 14 cm (Box 3)
    Available on Shared Shelf Commons: RMC2008_1148
  - "Der groe Totengrber", 1814; 48 (Box 3)
  - "Ach! Papa, welche schne seifenblasen hast du gemacht!", 1814; 49; Voltz, Johann Michael; 19.8 x 16.6 cm (Box 3)
    Available on Shared Shelf Commons: RM2008-1147
  - “Saute pour le roi”, 1814; 50 (Box 3)
  - "Je Fume en Pleurant mes Pchs", 1815; 51; 34 x 24.5 cm (Box 3)
    France (?)
- The First Bourbon Restauration (April 1814-March 1815) and the Cent-Jours (March-July 1815), 1814-1815
  - "La Colre du ciel est enfin apaise, nos Rois nous sont rendus", 1814; 52 (Box 4)
  - "Une visite de l'Ile d'Elbe, ou l'embarras de la toilette" [Louis XVIII and his brother, future Charles X], 1815; 53; 19 x 14.5 cm (Box 4)
  - "M. de la Rodomontade Apprenant le Dbarquement de l'Empereur", 1815; 54; 24 x 22 cm (Box 4)
  - "Dpart de Paris de Mr. de la Jobardire: Il est revenu! Filons!", 1815; 55; 24 x 22 cm (Box 4)
  - “Le Zélé Défenseur”, 1815; 56; 24 x 22 cm (Box 4)
  - "La Girouette", 1815; 57; 24 x 22 cm (Box 4)
  - "C'est aujourd'hui la St. Lambert qui quitte sa place la perd", 1815; 58; 39 x 26.3 cm (Box 4)
  - "Retour de l’Ile d’Elbe, Il Ramène la Liberté!", 1815; 59; 27 x 35 cm (Box 4)
- Second Restauration (1815-1830), 1815-1830
  - "La Balance Politique" [Congress of Vienna, 1815], 1815; 60; 31 x 43 cm (Box 4)
    Plate from “Le Nain Jaune”
  - “Serment des Nouveaux Horace: Nous le Soutiendrons!” [Louis XVIII], 1815; 61; 24.8 x 21.2 cm (Box 4)
  - "Ah quelle crise ! Soutenez-moi car je chancelle" [Louis XVIII, Blacas, and Montesquiou], 1820; 62; 23.3 x 18.3 cm (Box 4)
  - “A ton tour mon vieux!” [Charles X and Hussein Dey, Ottoman ruler of Algiers, 1830], 1830; 63
  - “Nouveau Journal des Modes: Coiffure a la Rambouillet inventée et exécutée par la population parisienne [pour Charles X]”, 1830; 64; 22.3 x 20.2 cm (Box 4)
  - “Armes du Grand Poulot” [Imaginary Coat of Arms of King Louis-Philippe I.], 1830; 65; Philipon, Charles; 34 x 25 cm (Box 4)
    Plate from "La caricature", nr. 63. Mentioned in the diary of Count Apponyi, the Austrian ambassador in Paris, 19 January 1832: "On a saisi hier une caricature: Les armes du grand Poulot; c'est un cusson bandes, une blanche entre deux vertes, deux btons tricolores avec un paon, queue dploye; pour support un cheval de carton, des capucins de cartes, arms de fusils, des canards de carte, enfin des joujoux d'enfants; pour couronne, un bonnet de papier avec un bouquet de lierre et pour devise: Bienheureux les pauvres d'esprit parce que le royaume est eux."
  - "Voici le pistolet qui a si longtemps amus le public, Voici la poire poudre, la poupe du tir et les drles de balles dont on s'est servi [after an attempt to assassinate King Louis-Philippe on November 19, 1832], 1832; 66; Desperet, Auguste; 24 x 20.7 cm (Box 4)
    Plate from "La Caricature", nr. 130
  - “Les Favoris de la Poire” [Louis-Philippe as a pear with two of his ministers, Antoine d’Argout and Felix Barthe], 1833; 67; Desperet, Auguste; 15 x 18.5 cm (Box 4)
    Plate from "La Caricature"
  - "Cabinet d’Histoire naturelle", 1833; 68; Grandville, J.J.; 35.6 52.1 cm (Box 4)
  - "N"oubliez pas le postillon, bourgeois: c’est juste, voici une poignée de main" [King Louis-Philippe as a penny-pinching bourgeois], 1835; 69; Roubaud, Benjamin; 25 x 23.2 cm (Box 4)
  - "Fte Nationale du 22 Septembre 1892: Le Char de la Concorde et de la Paix; le Char du Triomphe de la Rpublique", 1892-9-24; 70 (Box 4)
    Illustrated Supplement to "Le petit Journal" Inscription: “G.L. Burr, Esq., Ithaca, New York, en Amérique”